One big challenge that will be when we
don't understand what's going on in our
code base anymore, will that be a
problem or not? Some people are saying,
"Oh, that's not a problem because AI
will also maintain it." But I've also
run into situations where I've used a
prompt and because of my lack of
knowledge of what was going on in the
code base, AI actually deleted important
code.
>> I always say that code that was written
a day ago is legacy code. When we think
about true legacy code, we might want to
migrate frameworks. These are massively
different challenges that AI has to kind
of tackle.
>> In areas where you do legacy migration,
is that usually you don't feed the large
language model with the legacy code and
then turn it into new code in one step.
But usually what you do is you look at
how do we usually get from A to Z, from
the COBOL to the Java, and how can we
use AI on each of those steps on the way
there? And so we took it the same way
here. So we looked at first, how can we
reverse engineer in the sense of like
how can we create a comprehensive
description of what this application
does right now?
And then when we have that description,
how can we use that to do the forward
engineering?
>> Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
Now, we've had amazing guests like
Olivier Pomel, the CEO of Data Dog,
Matija Šoškić, the co-founder of Eleven
Labs, Victor Riparbelli, the CEO and
co-founder at Synthesia, and of course,
Tessels very own Patrick Dubois. And
they're all sharing lessons right from
the frontier of our industry. A really
quick ask, 90% of people who are
listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. It
really does help us keep bringing the
folks who are actually pushing this
space forward and helping build that AI
native future. All right, back to the
episode.
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI native dev. My name is Simon
Maple. I'm your host for the day and
joining me today we have Birgitta
Böckeler who is a distinguished engineer
at ThoughtWorks and today we're going to
be talking all about how AI can be used
not just
with you know new features that we're
building in our applications, but as
well as that looking more into the
legacy applications and how we can
unlock forward engineering with
code that is potentially lost the source
code, lost the engineers that actually
originally worked on that. All these
classic problems that we that we have
with legacy code. Birgitta, very welcome
to the AI native dev. How are you?
>> Hi Simon. Thanks for having me and I'm
well, thank you.
>> Absolute pleasure and so you're a
distinguished engineer at at
ThoughtWorks and you've
been an expert over the last few years
on how teams use AI or essentially
exploiting AI in software teams, how
they can get the most of it. You also
from what I understand
did some work on the on the tech radar.
You're one of the people who work on the
tech radar which is a super cool
way that people can really look at tools
and understand
which levels of maturity they're at and
and whether or not teams should you know
assess them, be adopting them, those
kind of things.
Talk us through a little bit about about
kind of like your role and how much fun
it is to or not fun it is to to put that
that tech radar together.
>> Yeah, so ThoughtWorks is a global
software consultancy, right? And also in
my professional like my full-time 20
plus years professional career I've only
worked in software consulting.
So I've seen like lots of different
organizations
build software and was part of a lot of
organizations building software.
Always like hands-on, you know, I'm a
PowerPoint consultant.
Um and um so at ThoughtWorks, I've been
there now for almost 13 years, but the
last 2 years I've had a full-time role
to just like,
you know, dive into the firehose of
generative AI and large language models
and how to use them for software teams.
And it's been uh a lot of fun, but also
quite intense. And, you know, it's very
interesting to be in a pressure cooker
like this in the hype, right, and try to
stay up to date. And I mean, yeah, one
thing that can keep me a little bit
grounded is the work on the technology
radar as well, which is like we publish
it twice a year in ThoughtWorks. Just a
snapshot of what we see at our clients
in the moment, right? Like as kind of
like
yeah,
compared to things like, you know, big
market reports, it's just a snapshot of
what we see, which can be useful, you
know? And uh actually in the last
edition, we had over 50% of the entries,
we usually put around 100 110 entries of
technologies and techniques that we're
seeing on it, over 50% of the entries
were generative AI related. So.
>> Did one of them did one of them make it
into the adopts this year?
>> I don't think so. I think one was in the
assess. Yeah, no no, but you know what
we have in adopt is actually retrieval
augmented generation.
>> Ah, okay.
>> Because, you know, when generative AI
first started, it started in assess
because it was like a new uh
technique, right? But it's it's also
like high-level and abstract enough that
even at this point, like still
relatively early in the in the
technology, right? It's something that
can go into adopt because it's just like
a a general technique that everybody's
using right now.
>> Mhm. Absolutely.
>> But that's the only thing, no tool.
>> Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Let's let's talk a little bit about uh I
guess how we have today um
worked with AI agents in our existing
workflows. And I'm I guess I'm
here I'm talking about active projects
and how we build
uh with agents in in that in that kind
of like uh typical software development
flow. Then we'll lean into more about
legacy uh applications, legacy
modernization. How do you see, you know,
you've got obviously got a lot of
experience from from many different
customers that you work with?
What what how do you see people using AI
effectively in their day-to-day
workflows today?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, I think before I answer the
question, maybe I should also emphasize
once more because it maybe didn't get
across quite yet that my focus is really
on using AI for building software to
improve how you build software, right?
Like not using AI in products, right?
Like putting building it into your
products. And it's always a little bit
clunky to describe that difference, but
I think it's a very important difference
to make because using AI for how we
build software affects everybody in
software development, everybody
involved, right? Whereas like putting AI
into your products only affects the
subset of people that actually work on a
product like that, right? So I see
myself as a domain expert in effective
software delivery, and I try to apply AI
to this domain, right? So that's kind of
just to focus it in on a little bit,
right?
>> It's such a subtle difference, but
really important. So at the AI native
dev, that's what we can that's what we
care about. We love we we we always
think about how you use AI in your in
your workflow. If it goes to production,
then it's then it's not the workflow.
It's actually part is the ingredients of
your app. If it if it if it does go to
production, but it's actually helping
the way you actually build and deliver
to production, then it's all about the
tools that you use in the workflow. It's
a subtle difference, but very important.
>> Yeah. And there's of course overlaps,
right? If you think of an big
organization that
has products and they want to build AI
into it and like for whatever their
context is that it's actually worth for
them to self-host models, have
guardrails, have evals, right?
You might also need those to build your
tools for, you know, using it in the
software process. So there's overlap,
but I think it's a it's a good
distinction to understand because
it really helps focus sometimes. And
yeah, so in that space when we talk
about agents, I would say really
that we have really agentic tools,
agentic agents, big words that often
mean very different things, right? But
it only really started, let's say,
exploding around February, March maybe,
I would say, right? So, a lot of the
coding assistant started releasing more
agentic tooling support in autumn last
year, I would say, October, November.
There were some open source tools that
already were doing it quite early, like
earlier last year, but you know, the
cursor, windsurf, GitHub copilot kind of
started end of last year. And then it
started getting into everybody's
consciousness with the vibe coding meme,
right? Like the
the Karpathy tweet was actually first
week of February, can you imagine?
That was 6 months ago.
>> Which year?
It feels like about 5 years ago.
>> Um so, that's when like this agentic
idea, right? Using that more in in
coding became more
um
of the the step change, I would say,
right? And what it means in coding
assistance is basically that the the
model gets access to even more tools
than it had before, right? So,
previously it was basically in the
coding assistance it could edit files,
um
yeah, I think it was mostly editing
files and often just one file at the at
the time.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh
and then now what we have is it can edit
multiple files, it can access the
terminal most importantly quite
autonomously and execute commands there,
execute your tests, and so on, and
immediately react to the
responses that you get from it, right?
So, it really expanded the size of the
task that a coding assistant can work
on. And so, either in like a session
with a developer going kind of like back
and forth, or then also a little bit
later, more of these products started
releasing autonomous
agents that you can run in the
background, right? So that was open AI
codex or cursor started introducing
these background agents.
As you know, very early Devon of course
was one of the first ones that did that.
So and it's becoming more and more
common in more and more products now. So
where you actually send it off by
itself, right? Without intervening in
between. So I think those are also two
that's also very important distinction
the autonomous ones and like working
with it myself in the in the workflow.
And like as a developer working with it,
I think that's the much more common one
as well at the moment. So and then when
you combine that with MCP servers, they
become even more powerful. They have
even more tools available. They can
access my test database or they can
browse the website in the browser and so
on and so on, right?
So and with this expansion in the size
of the task that we're working on um
everything kind of get becomes different
again. Like previously I was much more
thinking of it like I kind of go maybe
function by function, line by line and
AI is there to help me be faster. But
now AI is doing so much stuff that I
actually often fall behind, right? So
now there's like all of these much more
sophisticated new processes and ways of
working that we have to come up with as
developers to even come up and
make sure that something sensible comes
out of this.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And we have actually
essentially become the managers really
of those of those processes. Patrick
Patrick De Bois wrote really interesting
piece in around parallelization of these
agentic processes as well. Particularly
those that are kind of like the more
asynchronous that you you fire five of
these asynchronous
you know, agentic flows off and then
then they come back and you can
effectively review. Maybe they're doing
different things. Maybe they're doing
the same thing and you want to you want
to pick through which one which one you
actually want to take on.
But yeah, it's really interesting the
the new role that we're taking on which
we'll talk about a little bit later.
Um
so I guess
in in terms of, you know,
when when we when we have agents
um writing a bunch of code for us,
um it's very hard for us, I guess, to
feel almost like connected with that
code in terms of intimately knowing how
it's been built, because we tend to
click accept, accept, accept, and and we
and we don't tend to necessarily give it
the the the level of granularity of of
of checking as we as we want to. Um it
kind of almost immediately turns into
legacy code, right? Because when we
think about I you know, I always say
code that was written a day ago is
legacy code. It it's any any code,
really, that you don't fundamen- that
you aren't fundamentally actively
changing,
in my opinion, can kind of be considered
legacy because you have There are There
are tasks you need to do to actually
truly understand what is this code
doing, particularly if someone else
wrote it. What it What is this code
doing? What is it, you know, what what
what was in the developer's head when
when we first when we first kind of look
at this. And when we think about true
legacy code, where, you know, you may
not even have access to the source
still, but you have this, you know, you
you you have some application that's
kind of like running.
We might want to migrate frameworks. We
might want to change the platform it's
running on.
How do we These are massively different
challenges that AI has to has to kind of
tackle. How would you say
Do we use the same Should we use the
same tools to to to to make changes or
to even understand what legacy
um code is doing compared to forward
development or or should we look at a
completely different set of agentic
processes as well as tools?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, legacy migration or modernization,
I think, is a great example of um
like uh almost like uh initiatives and
larger projects that we can run where we
can really think through how do we use
agents or how do we use AI in general,
right? Uh uh in comparison to, you know,
just the day-to-day usage of a coding
agent, right? Where we have all of these
typical practices now. Oh, we plan, we
break down, and so on, right? Um but
there are like opportunities when we
have larger initiatives on our teams
like a legacy migration, which is I
think the best example. It can also be
other workflows, right? Where we can
actually
uh more sit down and think about, okay,
what is a workflow here? Like what uh do
we want to write prompts that we can
reuse again and again because we will
have to do this for 50 components or um
so I think that's where those two areas
we talked about before start overlapping
again as well, right? So now you
actually want to build an agentic system
that helps you with your initiative,
right? So now you have to know more
about like how do you build build an
agent yourself or what tools do you have
available, right?
And so I've recently worked um
on a uh on a few things related to uh
this legacy migration. Like the the the
first thing was that um
so we we did indeed have a client, like
you were saying, who said, "Oh, we
actually don't have the source code for
this application anymore."
>> Mhm.
>> So, you know, imagine like a bad vendor
breakup or
what it and it's apparently not that
uncommon, I've since found out.
And they said, "Okay, we haven't been
able to upgrade this application in
quite a while. We need to do something.
Can AI help us, right?"
>> Even if it's a legacy Even if it's a
security concern like
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> there are vulnerabilities that are
you know, all over the place that have
been found. It could be just general
maintenance, yeah.
>> Huge operational risk. Also, they
couldn't upgrade the database because
like the newer version of the database
had some like major changes in dialect
and so on. They couldn't change the SQL
queries that were in the code, right?
>> Wow.
>> Um
and so um what
we have seen now time and again uh in
areas where you do legacy migration,
also with those of our clients who have
large COBOL
code bases still,
is that
usually you don't go from you don't feed
the large language model with the code
just the legacy code and then turn it
into new code in one step. You don't do
that anyway, right? It's because just
too far away from each other, right? So,
but usually what you do is you look at
how do we usually get from A to Z,
right? From the COBOL to the Java. And
how can we use AI on each of those steps
on the way there, right?
And so, we took it the same way here.
So, we looked at first how can we
reverse engineer in the sense of like
how can we create a comprehensive
description of what this application
does right now?
And then when we have that description,
how can we use that to do the forward
engineering, right?
So, there's some things that
have been around for quite a long time
that are typical data capture approaches
that we do in legacy migrations also
before AI, like a change data capture,
right? So, in one of our experiments we
put just like triggers on the database
tables, had, you know, every update and
insert was kind of recorded into an
audit table.
And so that we could just see like in
the running application what happens. Or
maybe if you have an event-based system,
you could like capture events in the
running application. Or
what you can now also do with AI is you
can have AI browse through the
application, especially when it's a web
application. Doesn't always work as
easily as with a web application, right?
And can have AI describe what it sees as
it navigates through the application,
right? And have AI explore all the
different click paths.
And then you can tell it every time you
click after that, please check our audit
log in the database and see what changed
in the database when you click that
button, right? So, you can try and
create all of these uh
uh descriptions of what is happening.
>> It's It's almost like it's It sounds
like it's kind of like a
like a forensic exercise really, isn't
it?
>> Exactly. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> It's It's incredible. Like when when you
I guess first of all I got I got a
question in terms of the tools. Like are
there tools specific tools that you're
using for this or is this something that
you would expect needs to be needs to be
handcrafted? Um
and I and I guess my my second question
from that is when you when you gather
all this data
how do you how do you even think about
which context is most relevant? Uh so
that when you actually do the analysis,
you're not overwhelming the LLM with
that huge amount of
context, but you're providing it with
what it needs to make a good decision.
But I'd love to start with the tooling
one. How How would someone even think
about doing this?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, so I did uh we found that actually
you don't need like a fancy gigantic
platform to get started with this and do
something there. And my suspicion is
also that because of the nature of the
types of system where you have to do all
this forensics and that are really old,
right? They it's probably going to be
different every time, right? Just if you
think about I don't know SQL or even
COBOL or stuff like that. There's so
many dialects there as well, right? When
it comes to COBOL, for example, we have
a
an accelerator that we bring to our
clients in in ThoughtWorks that we
customize
uh every single time we use this for our
client. So where we say, "Okay, do you
need Do you have COBOL code? Do you have
C code? Do you have uh you know, a
particular dialect of some other
language, right?" And we load that into
a knowledge graph to get like a much
richer uh yeah, data set about what's
happening. And the um advantage of this
customization is not just that you might
have different languages, different
dialects, and so on, but also you can
decide based on the goal you have what
else what do you want to load into the
knowledge graph, right? So, just imagine
if you enrich the knowledge graph with
functional descriptions of the code
uh
by an LLM, right? Then, you can
actually, when you ask the knowledge
graph about things like what is
happening in the code base, what
validations are we using in XYZ,
if you get more functional answers back,
you can also provide this to a lot more
users, right? There's there are users
who don't want to know if the name of
the function or the module or but they
just want to know what's happening in
the functionality, right? Or you can
find ways to maybe
explore what are the different
capabilities here to find the seams to
break things apart, right? So, that
would be a more customized approach
where maybe you, you know,
you have really large code bases or you
have a specific goal or something.
>> Yeah.
>> But to get back to that idea to that
uh example I was talking about before
where you have lost the back-end code,
but maybe there's some other stuff,
right? So, what we did there is just
like work with an existing coding
assistant, right?
So, uh and just then point the coding
assistant at the things that we have
available, um and um
also use a few MCP servers. So, for the
web browsing, you can use something like
a Playwright MCP server where that also
like knows the DOM structure and doesn't
just go off of visuals, right? And then,
I also usually like to just create small
MCP servers on the fly because they're
really easy to create actually,
especially if it's like it's like a
little tool that you might throw away
later and you don't need it anymore,
right? So, that's what we did for
example for this data capture thing. So,
where the MCP server was just providing
a way to get a current timestamp and to
query that audit table.
And so then the agent could kind of go,
"Okay." Could get the current timestamp,
click on a button, and then ask the
audit table, "What changed since that
timestamp?"
>> Mhm.
>> So, that was the MCP server, right?
So, um
and I think that's really great because
the uh
in this combination of like coding
assistance, MCP servers,
you can actually then build your
workflow that you need, right? And
because that is so flexible, um
that helps us in the situation where
every legacy situation is slightly
different.
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
Inter- very interesting. And I guess the
question is with all of this, is the
goal then to create the specifications
or just to get the AI to enough
information to be able to develop
new new new features, new new make
changes on top of that?
>> Yeah.
So, um how we approached it is to in the
first step, which we call this like
reverse engineering step that just
creates a description, just create uh
very very comprehensive description.
>> Mhm.
>> And the reason for that is that then
when you have that description, you can
actually do more things with that
description, right? For example, you can
go to subject matter expert and experts
and sanity check if it's actually
correct, right? Cuz you might not even
have all of the information. In that
case with the client that didn't have
the back-end code anymore, we didn't
know what else is hidden in that
back-end code. Is it calling any other
services? We also tried our hand at
network data capture a little bit, but
not between services. So, um we actually
when we decompiled the code, we found
some uh some signs of like mainframe
frame calls, right? So, we had all of
this forensics, but now we needed
uh I don't know, somebody who lived in
the times back in the day when all of
this happened, who can like kind of uh
uh
double-check with us if it's actually
correct.
>> Yeah.
>> Or what you can also do then with that
specification is you can enhance it with
other things that you want to modernize
or change, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So, um
we have a team in ThoughtWorks that's
working on an open-source medical record
system applica-
application that is open-source and has
been around for a long time. And so
there's a front end that's still Angular
1.
So they really urgently needed to
upgrade the tech stack, but also they
wanted to include more compliance with a
standard in the medical records domain,
and they wanted to improve the what how
the front end looks, right? So now they
could they would go through the front
end components, create descriptions of
what they do today, and then enrich them
with those standard standard
requirements, and you know, how they
maybe wanted to change the UI, and then
use that to generate the new
Again, under supervision of a developer,
but you know, the developer would be
very accelerated.
>> Yeah, no, absolutely. I guess there's an
interesting piece there that that that I
think
sometimes is is easy to easy to to, you
know, pull someone in and and just say,
"Can you look at this?" and they'll
understand it, they'll know what's right
and wrong.
Uh sometimes we just don't have that
luxury like you say, you know, we have
to go back into the day and hope there's
a developer or someone who understands
that. Of course, with with legacy code,
the the
as we say, the what and the how are
combined together in the code, and it's
really hard to be able to identify, was
this written like this because for you
know, for for a reason? Was this part of
the the intended behavior? Or is this
just the implementation? And I guess
with One thing that really uh to some
extent allows us to understand that
expected behavior is tests. And tests
are ultimately the a great way of being
able to say, "Right, my change hasn't
regressed anything."
Um now, with legacy code, of course,
we're very very lucky if we have the
source code, let alone tests that come
along with it. What what in your opinion
or in your experience, like
how common is it to get
you know, a well-tested legacy or or a
legacy application with a good set of
tests that actually allow you to perform
a reliable change and get that
validation.
>> Mhm.
>> Um and and I guess lacking that,
how do you create that that safety net
essentially?
Whatever changes we make aren't going to
adversely affect parts of the
application we didn't even think about.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, this real case that I was
talking about, there were no tests.
>> No tests at all.
>> And also, even if for the back end,
let's say there were unit tests
somewhere. I mean, that doesn't help us,
right? Because it's unit level, right?
Like, the main thing that would have
helped us is if there had been like a
big end-to-end test suite or something
like that, right? And in fact, like what
we also looked into, but you know, it
hasn't progressed to the point that I
can say it was really successful or not,
is we also looked into, you know, does
AI
can AI help us accelerate building
almost like um
uh
fidelity fitness function. Using fancy
words, right? Like an end-to-end test
suite that can help us test parity that
we can actually point at both
applications, right? Um and I think on
the one hand, uh frameworks like
Playwrights or kind of like web browser
testing frameworks have become a lot
more tolerant to different selectors in
the DOM, right? But with AI, you can
make in theory make that even more
flexible, right? Like, so if you have
end-to-end tests that actually run on
AI, you can say um find the plus button
in the column.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? And it will try to look for that,
right? Whereas, so you don't even have
to use a selector, right? So, it gives
you a little bit extra um flexibility.
And also, our idea was maybe we can even
use that specification that we generated
with AI and use that as an input to
write that end-to-end test suite faster,
right? All with the goal of ultimately
having a test suite that we can point at
the old application and at the new
application. Right?
I mean, it turns out browser tests are
already notoriously flaky. It doesn't
necessarily help when you introduce more
non-determinism into it.
So, we didn't like we didn't yet like
push it far enough to say is this really
viable or not. I have a little bit of
doubts, but I think there's there's some
potential there. But, that's one way to
to do that. And then overall, it's like
a constant risk assessment, right?
Constantly when you do this, you think
about okay, what's the probability AI
got this wrong?
How can I mitigate that? How can I find
more information? Like, you know, we
decompile the binary to see if we missed
anything. How complex is the
application? What's the business impact
when something is wrong? Right? How what
else can you mitigate? Like, again,
classic legacy migration roll out
strategies. Like, can you do a staggered
roll out and start with some like
or maybe do like compare when the new
application is running for users,
compare results of the new one with
results of the old one. This is all
classic legacy migration stuff, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So, it is a constant risk assessment.
This particular application wasn't
particularly complex. So, that's like a
that's like the good news, right? It was
a bunch of forms.
If you have a more complex application,
then yeah, you have to also put a lot of
work into this risk assessment and
mitigation and like how do we
double-check and
what else can we do to test? Yeah.
>> And what And what is your What would you
say like from a success rate point of
view in terms of obviously simple simple
applications, you can kind of really get
an understanding of of what it should do
and and you know, I I would expect some
one once you have all that forensic
information, an AI bot or agent will be
able to come in and and and fairly
easily make certain changes that are a
low risk.
With a more complex application where
there are impacts if you make certain
changes in certain places,
>> Mhm.
>> what kind of like what's your success
uh expectation um for you know, not
obviously Yolo one prompting it but
>> Mhm.
>> it you know, does it does it take a lot
of iteration to to get there? Do you get
to a state where you know what, you're
actually really confident that there are
no regressions this can be fully
>> Mhm.
>> pushed out?
>> Yeah.
>> What's the end game?
>> So, with the simple application uh where
we only went through the kind of like
development and evaluation of an
approach, we didn't actually start um um
building it but uh I was really
impressed like how with the results,
right? So, like I said it was a bunch of
forms. We had front-end code, schema,
stored procedures, and the binary,
right? And screenshots.
>> Mhm.
>> And
uh it was really impressive and
satisfying how quickly you could get a
really comprehensive description that
also made sense,
>> Mhm.
>> And even um it was also really cool to
see uh
like two of my colleagues went deep into
the decompiled binary and like fed the
assembly code to AI
and navigated the assembly code together
and tried to find the function that, you
know, when you click this button, what
is the function that is being called,
right? Um and
>> on.
>> Did AI navigate the assembly code there?
So, uh there was a lot of manual
preparation work at first that they had
to do. So, to kind of like split
everything in more into multiple pieces
because you couldn't feed it like
everything at once. Assembly is also
super verbose, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Um and then you know, there were some
like uh
hints of where things were because you
could like see string names of stored
procedures or something, you know, so
you could have some hints. And then my
colleagues basically paired with AI to
try and like reason about the assembly
code and come up with hypotheses and
theories where this is and then to
actually find the code where they were
pretty confident that's that's where it
is. And so ultimately it was more like a
confidence booster for the results that
we already had from before where we had
AI infer what is happening, right? And
we would have later also been able to do
some change data capture which would
have given us even more confidence. But
like I said, they found things like,
"Oh, there seems to be a mainframe call
here. We should find out what what's
happening there, right?"
Yeah, and it was just super interesting
to see how well a large language model
could reason about what like could turn
the assembly code into pseudo code so
that we could read that as humans,
right? So
>> Yeah. It's It's amazing. It's kind of
scary at the same time when you say,
"Oh, look, there's a mainframe call
there." That's like It frightens the
heck out of me thinking, "Oh, gosh." All
these things that you wouldn't expect or
just just like find out.
It's incredible.
>> And also something in terms of the
confidence, something that we saw
we sometimes saw the large language
model that we were using often like
wasn't following our instructions very
well.
>> Right.
>> So
then what you would do is like you kind
of prepare your problems, what you want
to do, you know, so problems that say,
"Here's the front-end code. Here's the
screenshot.
You know, here's the schema. Try to
infer what's happening or like what are
the validations." You know, that's kind
of the questions the prompts would ask.
And then we would run those
multiple times for the same form, right?
To see like how different are these
results so that we could kind of see if
we get like basically the same result
every time, then we were relatively
confident that it was okay.
And
together with the human sanity check,
right? But so that's how you can kind of
see like the fidelity of your tool,
right? Is it like totally off the rails
or
does it give you something that seems to
make sense?
>> Yeah. And what are examples of like I
guess, you know, some of the some of the
more major changes that you've made in
terms of the legacy modernization?
You mentioned from COBOL to Java,
obviously, kind of pretty pretty major
pretty major, but also, I guess it's
it's a it's a fairly common but when you
think about modernization, it's it you
know, a COBOL to Java isn't the the most
unusual um
path, I suspect.
But is it like, you know, would you also
do things like framework updates and
things like that? Do you have complete
changes of architectures?
Anything anything kind of like more
major in terms of your forward
engineering?
>> Yeah. I mean, the framework upgrade was
kind of the example I
talked about before with Angular 1 to
React and then but then there was also
additional modernization that needed to
happen, right?
Um I think there's probably a lot of
different things that you can do when
you think about this as like, what are
my data sources that give me a
description?
Right? Which can be like a lot of
different things, right? Um
But maybe like when you talk about
framework upgrades, like there's a
slightly different category, I think as
well. Like when you just really think
like upgrade in the sense of just a
technical upgrade, right? Like Java
language upgrade or framework version
upgrade that's maybe not quite as uh
uh jarring as Angular 1 to the latest
Angular version, right? There's actually
uh tools that help you do that as well,
right? Deterministic software, right?
So, code mods like uh Open Rewrite or uh
uh Source Graph can do a lot of that
stuff. So, there's like
lots of tools that can help you write
recipes and advanced patterns to do
this, right?
>> Mhm.
>> And um
there's also really interesting
potential in combining large language
models with those code mod tools.
>> Mhm.
>> So, kind of either letting them help you
write the patterns that you need to do
the to do the upgrade.
Um
Yeah, or like like do that, right? Kind
of or and then where the where the where
the deterministic software that the
pattern
patterns just don't are not enough, then
maybe you try to fill that in with LLMs,
right? So, I don't know if you remember
a lot sometime last year there was big
headline by Amazon that they had saved
thousands of developer years
by using AI to do a Java upgrade.
But under the hood they were using
OpenRewrite.
>> Yeah.
>> Which is like one of those code mod
frameworks.
>> Yeah.
>> And my suspicion is that OpenRewrite was
doing a lot of the heavy lifting, right?
>> Fair enough, probably together with AI.
I'm not saying that whole setup, that
whole tool by Amazon was a bad tool,
right? Um
but I just found it a bit misleading to
say that AI has saved all of those
developer years, right?
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> The the pairing up of AI and like
good old software tools that we have,
that's where the magic happens, right?
>> And and I think that's where you kind of
like mix the creativity alongside the
determinism, which is really important.
And I think this is In fact, we had the
we had the the the CEO of Modern, who
they do a lot of
uh on on OpenRewrite on just the other
just the other day on the podcast. And
um yeah, he was talking about using how
they essentially use the AST, the
abstract syntax tree of the of the of
the application. And they're able to
kind of like truly understand the
deterministic flows through the app. And
I think particularly when we look at
something like this, when you think,
"Okay, there's a big there's a big
change that needs to be made. I want to
make sure the flows are going to be the
same uh or or or you know,
perhaps
in a slightly different more abstract
way, but
it it needs to effectively be a
deterministic yes, this is working the
same or no, it's not. And AI can't give
you that, but
mixing I love I love that you kind of
like mentioned that. Mixing this like
deterministic AST or existing tools that
we've been using for so long with with
the creativity of an LLM and being able
to kind of like, you know, make those
suggested fixes and and and and then we
test against more deterministic methods
I think is a is a really strong a really
strong plan. We've seen it time and time
again. Sneak does that as well and and
and Sneak code and many other tools have
that combination of determinism in in in
their AI solutions.
>> Yeah. And we have to think a lot more in
probabilities now in like on the meter
level as software developers, right?
Because of this. So if you think about
that situation where you cannot upgrade
an application anymore, which is a huge
risk, right? So it's better to replace
it and risk some bugs than not do
anything, right? But now you but you can
employ different things to accelerate
that replacement and to increase the
probability that you're getting it
right. Yeah? And then you constantly
have to kind of think about those
trade-offs and
and risks and how you fill the gaps and
so on.
>> That's a really good point. So like
obviously AI can kind of like will
you know more and more generate
more reasonable applications at scale.
Will we do you feel like we'll get to a
stage where a legacy app won't won't
ever exist anymore? It's just an app
that at some point we can just kind of
like it particularly for the you know
some of the smaller ones. Why would I
try and do all of this? Why wouldn't I
just why wouldn't I just rebuild this
from scratch? Do do you think like
that's in the in the near term going to
be a realistic approach
again you know you can build it on a
more modern app much much or a more
modern stack much much more quickly and
and the risk of what you know why pull
something from a legacy an old code
base? Why not just rebuild it from
scratch and understand exactly what's
happening under the covers?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, I think that that might happen,
right? Like it's
it's this effect that we can already see
with like organizations that have like
hundreds or thousands of microservices,
right?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> What I often see happening with
developers is they're working on a
service and when it gets to a certain
size, often that's not even that big.
They're like, "Ugh, this is too big. We
need to split this up. We need to create
a new one." "Ugh, we don't understand it
anymore. We can't reason about it
anymore." And then you end up with like
two entities in every service, right?
Which is also not the right way, right?
Like maybe we should just get a little
bit better at modularizing inside of our
services, right? But this psychological
uh how do you say uh reflex, this reflex
shows you that this might actually now
happen that, you know, people's reflex
will be to like, "Ugh, we don't
understand this anymore. Let's just
quickly rewrite it with AI, right?"
>> Yeah.
>> Which
maybe sometimes the, you know, sitting
down and actually seeing how can we make
this better might be the more effective
way to do it, right? Let's see.
>> Yeah.
Well, let's talk about humans and and
talk about how we as developers in the
loop, humans in the loop as we call it.
Um how we need to change to be better in
this process, to actually continue to,
you know, run this process.
There's a ton of stuff that we need to
be good at in order for us to actually
uh own the process and and and run the
process. Uh you mentioned a ton there in
terms of like getting a bunch of those
metrics and actually working with AI,
almost like pairing with AI to get all
that correct information. I guess it's
it's still an understanding of knowing
what information we need, what
information is important, uh and really
I guess understanding the application.
But um what else do we need to be better
at in order to
um or or learn new skills we need to
learn to be efficient and effective in
this type of in this new loop.
>> Mhm.
Yeah, that's a big topic. Also,
everybody's worried about the new people
coming into the profession and you know,
who who don't have the scars from like
from the past and you know how do we
build up new skills and I also don't
have the answers
to all of those things. It will be very
interesting definitely and I think for
experienced senior
developers and software engineers it's
now our responsibility to figure out how
we can do that for the next generation,
right? Because like experienced
developers don't just grow on trees like
we all develop by running into problems
and you know have being called up at
2:00 a.m. in the morning and then
thinking I'm not going to do that again,
you know.
Um
So yeah, like what are the skills? I
mean
um
One big challenge that we were talking
about this before will be this like when
we don't
understand what's going on in our code
base anymore, will that be a problem or
not, right? Some people are saying oh
that's not a problem because AI will
also maintain it, right?
But I've also run into situations where
I've used a prompt and because of my
lack of knowledge of what was going on
in the code base
I
it was a let's say subpar prompt and AI
actually deleted important code
because I wasn't aware of that
impact of that you know that oh I should
tell it but don't touch that, right?
Because so um
So that's going to be a challenge,
right? I think we should still
roughly understand what are the
components in our code, what is the
dependencies, what is when I change
this, how many other places are calling
that, so how risky is it to change that
and so on. Um
And then
uh
yeah, we
I hope we will get better tools to help
us review
large change sets, right? So we're used
to just reviewing text diffs.
Um
but maybe that's not scalable anymore.
And maybe there's even like new ways
with AI to help us
visualize more, to help us pull together
lots of like automated information that
before we didn't put together because we
thought, oh, I I went through all this
code, I wrote it myself. I don't need
that static code analysis, that coverage
information. I know what I did. But now
if I go for lunch
uh and I send off an agent and I come
back and it has changed 50 files, you
know, maybe I want a dashboard that
shows me
everything like uh you know, like an
impact analysis or uh you know, um
yeah, so I'm wondering about that. I
think we need more tools like that and
not just rely on this like text diff.
>> Um it's really interesting cuz I guess
it's it's the question of what we're
reviewing. Are we are we trying to
review code, which actually
testing would be a better validator for
or are we trying to test decisions? Are
we trying to review decisions? Um
uh and we almost like want to level up
uh
uh code uh uh reviewing to that decision
level and have almost like your your
code more tested through or validated
through tests. I think there's probably
a a
a journey that we need to go on for that
for that to be true, but
>> You have to review the tests.
>> Yeah. Yeah, 100%.
>> generates the test and I've seen AI do
make so many mistakes when building
tests like tests that, you know, don't
do anything, too much mocking.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh
maybe making the wrong assumptions in
the test data and then you think I have
a uh test that is green,
>> Yeah.
>> but the tests are actually testing
something that is wrong.
>> Yeah.
>> Right? Um so, that's on the next level.
Yeah, okay, generate all these tests,
but how do I actually know know know
that it did what I wanted, right? And
especially when it changed a lot of
things, how do I find out quickly?
>> Mhm.
>> And well
>> I was going to say biases is another
area in and around there, right? Where
where
you know, there's going to be
if we're if we're allowing AI to
could generate tests and do all these
things, generate code, and make
decisions, we need to be very aware of
our of the biases that in the decisions
that are being made within AI.
Is that something
you know, or rather, it is something
that we should absolutely be aware of.
How can we though? How how can we train
ourselves to to really look out for when
biases within the AI
having an adverse effect of you know, of
of what is being generated?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, there's the biases in the AI and
our biases as well, right?
>> Very true.
>> Like
in the in the AI when it comes to
coding, I don't know if I would call it
biases, but I've seen it do things like
fill in gaps in what I prompted it with,
fill those gaps with assumptions, right?
Like that's a thing or as we all know,
they're very sycophantic, they really
want to like please us and fulfill you
know, our task what we ask them to do.
So yeah, like
I don't I don't know if there's
something about biases as well when it
comes to domain logic. I haven't really
thought about that yet, right? Like
might it lead us to implement something
biased in the application, I hadn't
thought about that yet.
But then on the other side is our
biases, right? So for example, because
AI always frames everything so
confidently, right? That even though we
know it's a machine and it's a
stochastic parrot and all of that, we
still it influences us, right? Oh, it's
so confident confidently saying that's a
best practice. So it
must be a best practice, right? And
often we also just like skim over these
words and like our eyes see best
practice, blah blah, and then we're
like, oh yeah, sounds good, right? Or
you know, once we get a solution from
AI, we might be anchored to it, right?
And then it makes it harder for us
ourselves to imagine other solutions
when things go wrong, right? Or there's
a
strange sunk cost fallacy at play here
as well, right? Like AI generates a lot
of code and it doesn't really work and
then sometimes we spend 2 hours trying
to fix it instead of throwing it away.
Because it's already there, right? Ah,
but it's almost working. And so often
it's it's it's similar to like
fixing forward when your production is
broken versus reverting it, right? Just
reverting is so much faster just to fix
it, right? And that's what you have to
do with AI code a lot as well. So yeah,
critical thinking, going back to your
question about the skills, right?
Critical thinking and
yeah, understanding all these
probabilities and um
constantly getting over ourselves with
um
all of these psychological effects of
this manipulative technology, right?
Going to be
interesting.
>> Absolutely. And and of course it's not
just going to be us
that need to be better in in, you know,
as the human in the loop, but as a team
everything's going to you know, the
delivery's going to change. Um
the the speed at which we deliver, the
quality, um and and I guess from a
delivery manager point of view, when
everything's happening so so much faster
uh around around us, what do we need to
be more conscious of? What do we need to
What do
What
Are there any new best practices or
things that we need to be better at as a
team in order to do this uh delivery
um in more effectively?
>> I mean, all of the good engineering
practices that we've developed over the
decades, right? Still very much matter
and Jenny AI
amplifies indiscriminately, right? So if
you have like a bad setup, you might
just amplify that bad setup, right? And
if you have a good one
everything might go well, right? So this
speed that you were talking about,
that's going to be the linchpin kind of,
right? Like can you actually in your
organization with your pipelines, with
your processes, can you support
an increase in throughput, right? So, um
when, you know, can you test faster? Can
you fill the backlog faster? Um
can you actually deal with that when
you're starting from a continuous
integration setup that is flaky?
Right? Or test setup that is flaky,
right? So, um I think a lot of
organizations are still underestimating
foundation that you need and also good
repeatable automation to make safety
net, to make sure that things are still
going well. And um yeah, I mean, me as a
developer when I see AI go off the
rails, I often roll back, like I was
just saying, right? I try to like let go
and roll back.
But when you are a delivery manager or
product owner and suddenly your team is
like constantly like turning out more
stuff and all the moving pieces around
here are moving even faster, you can't
just roll back, right?
So, um yeah, I have a feeling that
uh we're still underestimating this
the control that we're losing, right?
Like, maybe that's just like
I mean, as humans we want to be in
control and maybe we also have to let go
in some places and just let AI do its
thing, but I have a suspicion that
that's going we're going to run into
trouble there with like when we just
lose control over what's going on
because so many agents are running
around doing stuff for us, you know.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, no, absolutely. Um
let's finish up with uh I guess the
age-old question, the hardest question
to answer. In terms of well, what what
happens to me as a developer? What what
What do I do? Do I Do I need to
go be a farmer somewhere or what should
I do? Should I
How does my role look in the future?
>> I mean, as you said at the moment, I
still see a lot of need for the classic
experience and skills, right? When I was
talking about the legacy migration and
you called it forensics, right? For the
forensics, you need to know where to
look. You need to know
you know to uh
where where the corpses are in the
basement, right? And include them in
your data sources.
>> And you mentioned you mentioned about
the junior versus the senior dev. I'd
love to see like it's almost like I love
to call it Martin Thompson
used the phrase mechanical sympathy. And
it's about about you know
having that sympathy of how things are
built underneath to actually be able to
have that have that ability to actually
understand how to use your tools or use
the system. I think if you was to look
at a junior versus a senior
individual in that forensics style
exercise, you know that the senior
developer is going to go to the right
path, the right pieces because they know
what they're looking for. The junior
will probably ask many good questions
but have so many many emissions
as well, right? And it's it's
it's interesting that when you when we
talk about that future developer role
the senior developer of today will be
well equipped for that.
>> How does the how does the junior
developer learn some of those skills?
>> exactly.
>> Do they do they just follow the
forensics of the developer of the senior
developer? It's it's a different level
of learning, I guess.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. And then I mean legacy
migration is a specific case where
you've always needed people who maybe
are still familiar with some of like
what is an application server, right?
>> Right. Yeah.
>> But
then in the like let's say in just that
day-to-day of building a current
application,
you need those skills when you're doing
those risk assessments I talked about
before, right? Like I constantly have to
ask myself, can I trust this code? How
much review should I do?
You have to think about do I have a
safety net? What can go wrong? What is
the business impact? How critical is
this piece of code? Is this complex? Is
this not complex, right? Those are also
very traditional developer skills,
right? So you're better at like
you're less reckless, let's say, maybe,
right? And but at the same time like as
as more experienced developers, we still
have to build up that experience with AI
to understand when can I trust it, when
can I not trust it, and so on, right?
And I mean, my hope is
that the people coming into the
profession now will learn just the way
we did. They will make mistakes and
learn from them, right?
Um and I just hope that the period in
which like maybe everybody's a bit more
reckless and like the you know, we just
increase the throughput of those
mistakes is going to be as short as
possible and then we all develop a lot
of critical thinking about this and it's
going to be better, right? But I
I mean, when I was an intern even before
I had gone to university, I was an
intern at a startup and I deleted the
production database,
>> It happens.
>> I mean, it's like ultimately their fault
for letting somebody who
was just like a beginner There was just
one environment at the time. There
weren't even multiple ones, right? But I
learned from that. I learned from that
that I cannot just run a random script
that might override all the tables,
right?
>> you I bet the first thing you said was I
bet the first thing you said wasn't why
did you let me do that? It was oh crap,
I've deleted the production database.
How do I get this back? And then you you
learn. Oh, okay.
>> Yeah, exactly. Yeah. The first thing The
first thing that happened is I had the
reddest face I ever had in my life.
No, but that's an extreme case, of
course, but that's how I learned, right?
Like I've done things wrong or I've seen
other people make mistakes in the past
and then go like and then that kind of
trained my intuition, my reflexes, my
like oh, maybe you should look over
there, look over there, right? So I hope
that that will still happen and that
still in teams will have that
environment where we can help others not
make those mistakes. That's my like
positive view of how we will still learn
this, right? But
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Let's see. In a way kind of like a lot
of these things that you were saying
about what we as developers will need to
still do,
remaining consistent, is great because
those are the hard things. The things in
which will change is how we go about
doing that. And instead of us writing
the code to to achieve those things or
building the infrastructure or the the
architecture to do those things, a lot
of those things can be done similarly
with AI. I think, you know, part of me
kind of like thinks, well, will we get
to those Will we get to those pain
points and problems quicker?
Um you know, if I was a If I was a
junior developer and I just allow AI to
do whatever, I'll still hit those
problems. I'll still learn about those
kind of things, and I'll maybe even do
it quicker.
>> But it might It might actually bring the
pain forward, yeah.
>> Yeah. I I I just I just won't be I can
blame AI versus me actually typing that
command to do whatever in the production
database. But but it's Yeah, it's It'll
be interesting to see how that how that
appears. But great to
I think great
great advice and great forethought in
kind of like seeing actually the harder
things that we need to do as developers
today,
irrespective of the implementations, are
still the hardest things that we need
that we will need to do in future. And I
think those I think I agree I think
those those those same needs will exist
and and and be there for us for
for many years to come, certainly.
Um
Brigitte, this has been This has been
very very enlightening, and it's good I
think it's really good to talk about
what is a real problem for so many,
particularly in, you know, the larger
enterprises, larger larger uh
um
organizations as well, that have to deal
with legacy legacy code on a day-to-day
basis. And and it's pretty a wonderful
to kind of like hear, particularly in
the the way you were describing how to
how to get that information and really
give AI as much as information as you
possibly can, using AI as a as a tool as
well to peer peer program and peer learn
um from that. Wonderful, wonderful to
hear to hear your your tactics and how
you how you go about that. So, really
appreciate having you on to the to the
episode this this week, Brigitta.
>> Yeah, it was fun. Thanks for having me,
Simon.
>> Absolutely no problem, anytime. And
thanks very much for all listening.
Looking forward to another topic next
week, so tune in then. See you soon.